In this assignment you will create a
この課題では、レンガ撃ちゲームを
brick shooting game using the power cube
powerCube や samoflange を用いて
and samoflange assets.
作成します。
You will learn about the rigidbody and
学習する内容として、Rigidbody および
collider components, the instantiate,
Collider コンポーネント、 Instantiate、
destroy and translate functions,
Destroy および Translate 関数、
as well as using prefabs.
さらにプレハブの使用についてカバーします。
For more details on these individual elements
個別の要素についての詳細については
see the lessons on them linked below.
下のリンクにあるレッスンを参照して下さい。
You'll need the Robot Lab asset package
このためには Robot Lab アセットパッケージが必要である。
for this. See the link on this page
もし持っていない場合は
if you don't already have it.
このページにあるリンクを参照して下さい。
To begin open the empty scene
始めるためには 空のシーンを開いて
and then go to File - Save Scene As
メニューの File - Save Scene As により
to save it as our new scene. Save it in to
新しいシーンとして保存する。プロジェクトの Scene フォルダに
the scenes folder of the project and call
保存して
it Brick Shooter.
Brick Shooter と名前をつけます。
As we've used Save As we are now inside
Save As を使用し後は
the Brick Shooter scene. Let's start by
Brick Shooter シーンの中にすでにいます。
making our wall of cubes.
キューブの壁を作成するところから始めましょう。
For this we'll use the power cube.
このためには powerCube  を使用します。
In the Models folder you will find various
Models フォルダの中には様々なアセットが
assets. So locate the asset called
あります。この中で
Prop_PowerCube.
Prop_PowerCube というアセットをみつけてください。
It looks like this.
次のように見えるはずです。
Drag and drop it in to the scene
シーンの中に ドラッグ＆ドロップして
and with your mouse cursor over the scene view
シーンビューの上にマウスカーソルを置いた状態で
press F to focus on it.
F ボタンを押してフォーカスをあてて下さい。
To begin we'll setup the lighting to work
始めるためには、ライティングが動作するように
with this. Place this object
セットアップをします。このオブジェクトを
on the Dynamic Objects layer
インスペクタの最上部で
at the top of the inspector
Dynamic Objects レイヤーに配置して
and in the mesh renderer for this object
このオブジェクトのメッシュレンダラにて
check the box for Use Light Probes.
Use Light Probes チェックボックスを有効にして下さい。
Let's position this first brick in the wall
壁の最初のブロックの配置を
at (-3, 0.5, 0).
(-3, 0.5, 0) にして下さい。
Again you can always reselect your object
Hierarchy でオブジェクトを再選択して
in the hierarchy and with your mouse cursor
シーンの上にマウスカーソルをおいて
over the scene, press F to refocus.
F ボタンを押して再度フォーカスをあてる必要があります。
Now that it's nicely lit we'll add a
ライティングが適切に行なわれている今、
collider and rigidbody component to
コライダおよび Rigidbody コンポーネントを追加して
give it a physical mass.
物理的な重み (Mass) を与えることが出来ます。
Using the Add Component button on the inspector
インスペクタの Add Component ボタンを使用して
go to Physics and Box Collider
メニューから Physics -> Box Collider を選択して
and then Add Component again
Add Component を再び選び、
and choose Physics - Rigidbody.
さらに Physics - Rigidbody を選択します。
We'll be making many of these power cubes
この powerCube は複製を通して壁を構成するのに
via duplication to form our wall.
多く使用します。
But we may want to go back and adjust
しかし戻ってプロパティを
properties for all of them, so we should
全て調整したいため
turn this into a prefab now.
このときにプレハブにする必要があります。
Drag and drop this object into the
オブジェクトをドラッグ
Prefabs folder in the project panel.
プロジェクトパネルの Prefab フォルダにドロップします。
This saves the object as a prefab
これにより オブジェクトがプレハブとして保存され
and we'll rename it to differentiate it
モデルと区別するために
from our model. We'll call it
別の名前にします。
Physics_PowerCube
Physics_PowerCube と名前をつけます。
because it has the two crucial components,
ふたつの重要なコンポーネントである
the collider and the rigidbody
Collider および Rigidbody があるため
which mean that it's controlled by
つまり 物理エンジンにより制御
the physics engine. You should note that
されています。これをプレハブとしたため
because this is now a prefab it's text
テキストは Hierarchy ビューでテキストは
is shown in blue in the hierarchy.
青文字で表示されます。
Now let's make the duplicates of this
それでは壁を構成するために
to form our wall.
複製をしていきましょう。
Select the object in the hierarchy
Hierarchy ビューのオブジェクトを選択して
and we'll use the hand tool briefly to zoom out.
ハンドツールを少し使用してズームアウトする。
We can duplicate this by going to
これを複製するには
Edit - Duplicate
メニューから Edit - Duplicate を選択するか
or by using shortcut Control-D on PC
PC では Ctrl + D、
or Command-D on Mac.
Mac では Cmd + D のショートカットを使用します。
Now we're going to position the bricks
これからスナップを使用して壁の
in our wall by using Snapping.
レンガを配置する。
You can use snapping by holding down the
スナップを使用するには、Mac では Cmd キー、
Command key on Mac or Control on PC
PC では Ctrl を押さえたままにして
and by dragging with the Translate tool
位置調整ツールを使用してドラッグできます。
You can see that if I hold down the key
キーを押さえたまま
and pull the handle the object only moves
ハンドルを引っ張ることによりオブジェクトは
in increments of 1. And because our object
1 単位づつしか移動しない。そしてオブジェクトは
is modelled to a scale of 1 it will snap
1 のスケールであるようにモデリングされているため、
in to that position perfectly. We will
その位置にピタリとスナップする。
then continue to repeat this step
次に最初の行に 7 つ出来るまで
until we have 7 in our first row.
このステップを繰り返します。
Duplicate
複製して
Command drag or Control drag to snap.
Cmd ドラッグまたは Ctrl ドラッグをすることでスナップします。
Duplicate, snap drag
複製して、スナップしてドラッグ
Duplicate, snap drag and once more.
複製して、スナップしてドラッグ、そしてもう一回繰り返します。
This is our first row of cubes.
これが最初のキューブの行です。
And to organise them nicely we're going to
次にきれいに整理するために
create an empty game object to
空のゲームオブジェクトを作成して
store our row. So go to Game Object - Create Empty
行を格納させます。メニューから Game Object - Create Empty を選択して
hit the Return key on Mac or F2 on PC
Mac 上で Return キーまたは PC 上で F2 キーを押下して
to rename and we'll call this Row.
名前を変更し、 Row という名前にします。
I'm going to position this in the middle of our row,
これを列の真ん中に位置します。
so we'll place this at (0, 0.5, 0).
(0, 0.5, 0) に配置します。
Then to add our power cubes to this row
行に powerCube を追加するために
we will select them,
まとめて選択をして
so select the first one, hold down Shift
最初のものを選択して、Shift キーを押したままにして
and select the last.
最後のものを選択します。
And then drag them on to the row in the hierarchy.
これらを Hierarchy ビューの行の上にドラッグします。
Now they are all child objects of Row.
これらは全て Row の子オブジェクトとなりました。
Now we can conveniently duplicate Row
あとは Row を便利に複製して
and use snap drag in order to
スナップしてドラッグを使用することで
create the rest of the wall.
残りの壁を作成します。
So select Row in the hierarchy,
Hierarchy ビューの Row を選択して
and duplicate.
複製します。
Snap drag up
スナップして上にドラッグ、
and continue this until we have 5 rows.
これを 5 行できるまで繰り返します。
Now that our wall is complete, let's work
壁が完成したので、次は
on our projectile.
発射物を作成します。
In the Models folder find the 'prop_samoflange'
Models フォルダから prop_samoflange アセットを見つけて、
asset and drag it in to the scene.
シーンにドラッグします。
Let's drag it up so that we can see it
上にドラッグしてみえるようんしいて
and hover and press F to focus.
ホバーをして、 F キーを押してフォーカスをあてます。
We'll set up the lighting by putting
ライティングをセットアップするために
it on the Dynamic Objects layer
Dynamic Objects レイヤーにのせて
and checking Use Light Probes
メッシュレンダラで
in the mesh renderer.
Use Light Probes を有効にします。
We need this to be a Physics Object as well
これもまた Physics Object とする必要があります。
So go to Add Component - Physics - Sphere Collider
Add Component - Physics - Sphere Collider を選択して
and then Add Component - Physics - Rigidbody.
そして メニューから Add Component - Physics - Rigidbody を選択します。
Our projectile is now ready but because
発射物は準備ができているが、
we're going to use a script to create and launch
スクリプトを使用して作成および発射をするため、
this we do not want it in the scene when
開始時にシーンはないようにします。
it begins. So let's save this as a
これもまた
prefab as well.
プレハブとして保存します。
Drag it from the hierarchy and drop it in
Hierarchy ビューからドラッグして
to the Prefabs folder. Then we'll rename
Prefabs フォルダにドロップします。次に名前の変更をして
this Physics_Samoflange as well.
これも Physics_Samoflange とします。
You can now delete this from the scene
これをシーンから削除するには
by selecting it in the hierarchy
Hierarchy ビューで選択をして
and using Command-Backspace on Mac
Mac では Cmd - Backspace を押下するか、
or Delete on PC.
PC では Delete を押下します。
Now let's setup our shooting mechanic.
これで撃つためのメカニックをセットアップします。
Begin by expanding the Cameras object
最初にHierarchy ビューで Camera オブジェクトを拡大して
in the hierarchy and select Camera 01.
Camera01 を選択します。
We will reposition this camera at (0, 3, 10).
(0, 3, 10) に再配置します。
And set the rotation to (0, 180, 0).
回転を (0, 180, 0) にセットします。
So that now our camera - as you can see
ゲームビューで分かるように
in the game view - is facing our wall of bricks.
カメラはレンガの壁のほうに向いています。
Because our camera will move around and shoot
カメラは移動してレンガの壁に向かって
at the wall of bricks we'll place the
撃つためカメラに向かって撃つコードを
code for the shooting onto the camera.
配置します。
So let's go to Add Component - New Script.
このため Add Component - New Script を選択します。
And we'll call this script Shooter.
そしてこのスクリプトを Shooter と名前をつけます。
Double click on the script icon in order
スクリプト アイコンをダブルクリックして
to open it for editing.
編集のために開きます。
We do not need the Start function for this
このために Start 関数は必要ないので
so we'll begin by removing that
始める時に削除して
and also remove the comment
Update 関数の上のコメントも
above the Update function.
削除します。
We'll begin with some public variables
いくつかの public 変数で始めて
so that you can tweak settings or assign
インスペクタで設定を調整するか
prefabs in the inspector.
プレハブを割り当てます。
First, add a public Rigidbody
最初に public である Rigidbody 型の変数を
variable called Projectile.
追加して Projectile と名前をつけます。
We will drag and drop our Physics Samoflange
physics_samoflange プレハブをこの上に
prefab on to this and use it in our
ドラッグ＆ドロップして
instantiate function in order to create
Instantiate 関数に使用して
instances of our projectile.
発射物のインスタンスを作成します。
Next add a public transform variable
次に public である Transform 型の
called shotPos.
shotPos 変数を追加します。
We will create an empty game object
空のゲームオブジェクトを作成して
to store the position to shoot projectiles from
発射物を発射する位置を格納して、
and assign it to this variable later.
この変数に後ほど割り当てを行ないます。
Next add a public float
次に public である float 変数
called shotForce
shotForce を追加して
and set it to 1000.
値に 1000 をセットします。
We will use this to define the amount of
次にこれを使用して発射する
force to shoot with.
力の強さを定義します。
And finally add a public float called
そして最終的に public である float 型の変数
moveSpeed and set this to 10.
moveSpeed を追加して値を 10 にセットする。
This will define the movement speed of the
これによりカメラの移動速度を定義して
camera to aim the shots.
撃つ狙いを定めます。
All of our operations must be immediate
全ての処理は即時である必要があるため、
so we'll perform them inside the update function.
これは Update 関数の中で処理を行ないます。
Start by adding two variables to
初めに二つの変数を追加して
represent the horizontal and vertical
Horizonatl および Vertical の
input axes.
の Input Axis として使用します。
These are float variables called
これらの float 変数は
H and V.
H および V とします。
These are multiplied by Time.deltaTime
これらに Time.deltaTime を掛け算して
for smoothing. And then multiplied by
スムージングを行ないます。さらに
moveSpeed to increase the speed.
moveSpeed を掛け算することでスピードを増加させます。
We'll then use these values inside
さらにこれらの変数を
the translate command in order to move
Translate コマンドを使用して
the camera around. So we'll say
カメラを動かします。まずは
transform.Translate and create a new
transform.Translate を記述して新しい
Vector3 with the values of H and V
Vector3 型の H および V の値を入れて
as components of this vector.
Vector の構成要素とします。
So we'll be using the horizontal axis
Horizontal Axis を使用して
to move the X axis of the object
オブジェクトの X 軸上を移動し
and the vertical axis to move the Y axis.
そして Vertical Axis を使用して Y 軸上を移動します。
To fire our projectile we'll add
発射物を発射するため
an IF statement that waits for the release
if 文を追加して Fire1 ボタンが離されるのを
of the fire1 button,
待ちます。
which by default is the left-hand
これはデフォルトではキーボードの
Control key on the keyboard.
左 Ctrl キーとなっています。
Into this we'll add our instantiate function
この中に instantiate 関数を使用して
to create the projectile instance
発射物インスタンスを作成し
and then add a force to it.
さらに Force を追加します。
To begin, create a Rigidbody variable
初めに Rigidbody 形の変数
called Shot and set it equal to
Shot を作成して Instantiate 関数に
our instantiate function.
等しくします。
In this function we need the object
この関数では作成するオブジェクト、
to create, the position and the rotation
位置、および回転の
as it's three arguments -
3 つの引数が必要です。
So we'll use our projectile variable,
発射物の変数である
our shotPos transform's position
shotPos の Transform 位置および
and shotPos's rotation.
shotPos の 回転を使用します。
We finish the instantiate line by adding
Instantiate 関数の行を完成するには
'as Rigidbody' in order to cast the result
as Rigidbody を追加して結果を型キャストして
of this to the rigidbody data type.
Rigidbody 型に変換します。
This is because the standard instantiate
これは Instantiate 関数は
function returns an object
オブジェクトを戻り値とするためであり、
and we know that the type of our instantiated
一方でインスタンス化されたオブジェクトは
object needs to be a rigidbody.
Rigidbody である必要があります。
Finally we use the Rigidbody variable
最終的に Rigidbody 型の変数である
'Shot' to address that instance of our
Shot を使用して格納された
projectile stored in it and add a force to it.
発射物のインスタンスをみつけて力を追加することが出来ます。
We do this in the forward direction of
shotPos のTransform の
the shotPos transform,
Forward 方向で行ない
and multiply it by shotForce.
さらに shotForce を掛け算します。
Now let's save this script and return to Unity.
それではこのスクリプトを保存して Unity に戻ります。
Reselect the camera and you'll see that our
カメラを再度選択して、
public variables can be seen
public 変数を Script コンポーネントで
on the script component.
みることが出来ます。
Let's start by assigning the physics samoflange
最初に physics_samoflange を
from the prefabs folder that we made earlier
先ほど作成したプレハブから
to the projectile field.
発射物のフィールドに割り当てます。
Next we need to add a transform to our scene
次にシーンに Transform を追加して
to represent the position and direction
撃つ位置および向きを
with which to shoot.
表します。
Create an empty game object
空のゲームオブジェクトを作成するには
by going to Game Object - Create Empty.
Game Object - Create Empty を選択します。
We will rename this shotPos
これを shotPos と名前をつけて
and then drag and drop it on to camera 1
camera_001 の上にドラッグ＆ドロップして
to parent it beneath it.
その下の子オブジェクトとします。
Let's reset it's transform so that it
Tranfrom をリセットして
matches that of the camera.
カメラとマッチングするようにします。
You can see if I zoom out now
もしズームアウトすると
that the camera is positioned here
カメラがここに配置されて
and if I select shotPos,
shotPos を選択すれば、
click on the cog icon and choose
歯車アイコンをクリックして
'Reset', then all of the values for the
Reset を選択すると、Transform の全ての値は
transform are reset to a default.
デフォルトの値にリセットされます。
And now if I choose the translate tool
これで位置調整ツールを選択すれば
you can see that it is at the exact same
カメラとまったく同じ位置であることが
position as the camera.
確認できます。
But we need it to be slightly forward
しかしわずかに前方および
and slightly lower, and also tilted up
わずかに低い位置、さらには少し上向きの傾きに修正しないと
in order to aim shots from below camera
カメラの下から撃って、壁に向かった曲線を
in an arc pointed at the wall.
描くことが出来ません。
So we'll set the position of shotPos
shotPos の位置を
to 0 in X, -0.5 in Y, and 1 in the Z axis.
(-0.5, -0.5, 1) にセットします。
As you can see this places it
みてのとおり、これで
forward of the camera.
カメラの前方に位置されます。
Now we'll tilt it up by putting
次に上向きの傾きに修正するため
-15 in to the X axis.
X 軸に -15 を入力します。
Now reselect the camera, as this is
次にカメラを再選択して
where our script component is and drag
ここにスクリプトコンポーネントがあり、そして
and drop shotPos from the hierarchy
Hierarchy ビューから shotPos をドラッグ＆ドロップして
and drop it on to the variable shotPos
Shooter スクリプト コンポーネントの
on the Shooter script component.
shotPos 変数にドロップします。
And that's it, our script is now ready for use.
これで完了であり、スクリプトは使用する準備が出来ました。
Save your scene by going to File - Save Scene
シーンを保存するにはメニューから File - Save Scene を選択して
and then press play to test out the game.
Play ボタンを押下してゲーム再生をします。
Remember that the cursor keys,
方向キーとして
or W, A, S and D on the keyboard
キーボードの W, A, S および D キーが
are the defaults for horizontal and vertical.
Horizontal および Vertical のデフォルト値であることを覚えて下さい。
and that the left control key is fire1 - the key to shoot.
左 Ctrl キーが Fire1 にあたり、このキーにより撃ちます。
One thing we can do is to tidy up our
ひとつできることは散在している発射物を整理することです。
stray projectiles - as we continue to shoot
撃ち続けている間は
we are adding rigidbody objects to the scene
シーンに Rigidbody オブジェクトを追加しているため、
so we should really tidy these up
これらは整理すべきです。
because otherwise we are adding more and more
そうしなければ物理エンジンで
for the physics engine to keep track of,
管理しないといけない対象が次々と増えてしまい、
which will eventually effect performance.
最終的にパフォーマンスに影響します。
Press play to ensure you are no longer
Play を押すことで
in play mode and then select the physics
Play モードに入っていないことを確認して
samoflange in the prefabs folder.
Prefabs フォルダの physics_samoflange を選択します。
Scroll to the bottom of the inspector
インスペクタの下にスクロールして
and click Add Component then choose New Script
Add Component をクリックして New Script を選択して
and name this script Tidy.
このスクリプトの名前を Tidy にします。
Double click the icon to open it for editing
アイコンをダブルクリックして編集のために開き、
and for this, all we need is our Start function.
ここで唯一必要なのは Start 関数です。
So we can remove the Update function
Update 関数を取り除いて、
and we'll also remove the comment.
さらにコメントも取り除きます。
When this object enters the game we simply
このオブジェクトがゲームに登場するとき、
need to use the Destroy command
Destroy コマンドを使用して
and we'll destroy the game object this is
そしてアタッチされているゲームオブジェクトを破棄します。
attached to - the ball itself.
すなわちボール自身を破棄します。
And because we don't want it to happen
そしてこれはオブジェクトがゲームに登場した瞬間には
literally when the object enters the game
起きてほしくないため
we will use the second argument of the
Destroy コマンドの
Destroy command, which is the timed delay.
二つめの引数を使用して、遅延したタイマー実行を行ないます。
And we'll place in 5 seconds.
これを 5 秒と設定します。
We'll save our script
スクリプトを保存して
and return to Unity
Unity に戻ります。
Now you should notice that when you
これでゲームをテスト実行すると、
play test the game, once you have fired
いくつかの 発射物を撃った後、
a few projectiles they eventually
それらは最終的に
remove themselves from the game after they've
5秒後に
existed for 5 seconds. You can
ゲームから破棄されるこの気付きます。
see that by watching the hierarchy
Hierarchy ビューをみることで
these objects are being removed from the scene
これらのオブジェクトはシーンから削除されて
and they disappear from the scene and game views.
シーンやゲームビューから消えます。
So that's our brick shooter complete.
これで Brick Shooter は完了です。
Remember to save your scene
シーンを忘れずに保存して、
and try experimenting with different objects
異なるオブジェクトで撃つことを試したり、
to fire, or different rates of fire
撃つパラメータを変更したり
or different movement for the camera
またはカメラの異なる動作を試してください。
and if you didn't understand any of the concepts
そして、もしこの課題で分からなかった概念が
in this assignment check out the links
あった場合、以下のリンクにある
to the lessons below.
レッスンを確認して下さい。 (翻訳:gamesonytablet)